all right welcome back slw welcome back
to cohort
6 couple quick updates as we
mentioned with octopus and others there
are math discussion sessions they're
Tuesdays at 12
UTC octopus session videos has the links
to the
videos so feel feel free um these should
be awesome freewheeling and super
epistemic
sessions and as with the material on the
book itself all kinds of questions from
the most background and basic and
confirmatory for one on through the most
speculative and and farsighted for for
others it's always a contribution to to
write it down and as the math comes to
play and The Meta math and the math art
it's going to be a great journey
together um today we're in our
second pass on chapter six which is the
recipe for active inference modeling and
also a new or different feature in this
interval of activity compared to
previous weeks is the uh third week
Rhythm so in the
uh third week for cohort 6 going through
the second half of the book will really
focus on applying active inference
Andrew has written a tutorial utilizing
PDP with a focus on agent based modeling
for the social sciences so that should
be pretty cool and additionally as uh RX
and fur development continues we'll be
learning more and more about that um in
cohort 7 we haven't quite determined
what the third week activity will be in
that uh slot so we'll find out uh
discuss later today with that cohort and
and see what's useful in the third week
for now though let's uh jump over to
chapter
six we can start with
any section of six any idea or page or
figure in chapter
six that anybody wants to bring
up we could look at any of the prior
questions and also as chapter six is
about applying and designing active
inference models it it can be any
question that someone has so just raise
your hand or write it in the chat or
unmute and go for it
okay I'll just give one brief catch up
to get us to six to to get us uh there
in just a minute and then again just
type a question or raise your hand so
part one of the book they outline as
kind of the epistemic and the background
and learning part two is heading kind of
home stretch heading downhill heading
back home in into the applying chapter 1
and chapter 10 are like book ends
they're very similar chapters chapter 10
is a bit more broad ranging and longer
whereas chapter one introduces the ideas
whereas they're similar because they
provide
perspectives in chapter one this concept
of the low road and the high road is
introduced and that's Revisited in more
detail in chapters two and three low
road is like the how and the what it's
the actual architectures that are built
it's the way that base theorem applies
to perception and cognition and action
in a unified cognitive model and then
the high road comes from the free energy
principle physics of cognitive systems
basian mechanics the imperative to
persist to remeasure and so
on chapter 2 and three get us to active
inference and chapter four is where we
actually see the active inference
generative model itself which is what's
going to be given the recipe for in
chapter
6 chapter V goes through the generative
model describes some of its analytical
properties and introduces us to the idea
that there's a discrete time and a
continuous time form chapter five
message passing in neurobiology gives a
quick review of one of the systems of
interest that has received the most
study to date in terms of active
inference modeling which is like Maman
and human
neuroanatomy that's part one of the book
part two of the book goes into applying
active inference chapter six is very
provocative and fun and it's a recipe
for Designing active inference models
and as we'll I hope unpack a little bit
today it doesn't require some advanced
level of programming or anything like
that to to get going and actually with
augmented coding with templates and some
other tools there's a lot that can be
done just through conversation with the
domain expertise or familiarity and the
active inference
ontology chapter seven and eight then
are going to focus on some of the
features and examples of discrete time
continuous time models chapter nine
introduces data into the picture how do
empirical data relate to generative
models and then again chapter 10 is a
summary so that's the
textbook it's it's a long pull and then
when we kind of pull back to this level
of course graining it looks really short
too
so what's a section or a question on six
that that anybody would like to go to
okay we'll just go to the questions that
have been sorted by the thumbs
up you can click on the the symbol to
follow wherever uh a person is in Koda
and I'm putting it in the chat as well
so if you want to you can hit thumbs up
for the questions that are interesting
or again just like type it or raise your
hand
okay first
question what are the four steps in the
recipe to construct an active inference
model does anyone want to give a thought
on this
how are these steps similar or different
to any other kind of systems modeling or
analysis technique that people have seen
e e
okay uh John
okay let's look at figure
6.1 John go for it if you want to yeah
yeah sorry I had to set up properly
there um I'm I'm dealing with something
at work right now so I'm gonna be like
in and out on this um but a a question
I've kind of had come up and maybe this
is just from not seeing too many um
active inference agents implemented yet
is sort of how how do you fit expected
free energy in
with um free energy
minimization like for the current state
um versus looking into the future um
it's not something I saw detailed a ton
in chapter six
um but yeah and I guess answering the
question you posed um I think the like
looking at our we don't have you know
reward-based policies but we just focus
on minimization of fre energy expected
fre
energy um but yeah
like it's a little unclear to me how
those two
interplay um what what their interplay
is in
implementation great great question yeah
it's gonna it's gonna touch on a lot so
if if anybody wants to like add in or or
or going deeper into it some of this
please just write it or raise your hand
um otherwise let's get there so the
question is how do we think about free
energy minimization so the realtime free
energy minimization with equation 2.5
and the prospective expected free energy
minimization in equation 2.6 so how do
those pieces come together in an active
inference generative model okay let's
start with figure
6.1 this is called the particular
partition it's a pun particular means
like that specific one also particular
means related to a particle and the
agent or the cognitive particle is
consisting of the internal States and
the blanket States so everything to the
exclusion of the external States is
called the particle blanket plus
internal equals particle so it's like
the brain and the skin so to speak
that's figure separated from ground
that's the agent separated from the
niche that's called the particular
partition and the free energy principle
makes this kind of axiomatic starting
point that we're going to partition
systems according to a blank and the the
two directions there so this is kind of
the the partition on what we're looking
at okay
now how is free energy minimized in in
real time and where does planning and
prospection come into this we have some
external State let's say it's the actual
temperature of the room sensory States
coming in that's like thermometer
readings internal States like internal
representations of temperature and then
action states which be like to modify
the air conditioner that's kind of the
setup of the model
David uh yeah I was just wondering how
uh discret time would play in the um
exchange between the different states in
terms of being able to model fit for
example yeah great question um the way
it comes into play in discreet time we
think about each of these nodes having
like a number and then there's a
discrete tip of the model and like all
the numbers update in a tick in
continuous time these four states are
thought of as being like four
simultaneous
flows so it's like the difference
between like four discreetly updating
synchronized changes and like four
analog control knobs that are kind of
always giving a value and then they can
change
independently okay so now let's look at
the recipe then we'll get to equation
2.5 and
2.6 in the recipe first we identify the
system that we're modeling this is the
cognitive
particle that's that's or it's really
the cognitive particle plus Niche it's
the total setting and then question
three is basically how are we going to
set up the particle in terms of the
blanket and the internal States and
question four is how are we going to set
up the generative process
in terms of the niche so these four
questions basically just get us to the
point of
specifying the
agents including blanket and the niche
okay so how how does framing things in
that way relate to the real time
inference and uh to prospection
part of the answer is that it depends a
lot on the system that we're discussing
so it's kind of sometimes frustrating
the general in general but it's because
it depends so much on the system that
we're modeling so here we see a slightly
different representation of the
particular partition also of course
slightly different notation Etc and this
is like a Continuum from simpler systems
on through systems that have uh
introspection or it can have planning
but the overall scheme is is very
similar okay so John asked where does
expected free energy fit in let's look
at the equations for it and then we can
look at the pmdp documentation to see
what it looks like
equation 2.5 is the variational free
energy variational free energy it's a
functional so it's a function that takes
in a function and what it takes in is q
a belief distribution and why a new
observation data coming in so this is
like the agent's
belief about temperature distribution
that could be a super tight distribution
very loose distribution and then Y is a
data point and here are three equivalent
ways to frame this or to to decompose
the same
quantity the
top uh line is using a physics based
ontology of energy minus
entropy the middle is using a
statistical ontology of complexity minus
accuracy which is to say we want to
reward models for fitting well however
we want to penalize them for having more
parameters that's also known as the I
key information Criterion or the Baye
information Criterion basically in that
adding more parameters will always fit
the data better so the imperative can't
Simply Be Fit the data better otherwise
you take that to the end of the road and
you just have this massively overfit
model so the question is how do you
penalize a model for its growth while
rewarding it for fitting well and that's
the kind of accuracy minus
complexity uh trade-off Frontier and
then there's a Divergence in evidence
representation these are not look ahads
this just relates to beliefs at a time
point and an incoming data point that's
because variational free energy is
attractive
optimizable bound on surprisal surprisal
itself is often difficult to compute
because it it can be a large computation
however variational free energy is this
tractable bound this is not introduced
or invented by active inference
variational
autoencoders any kind of variational
inference uses the exact same
approach it's known as the evidence
lower bound or the variational lower
bound so if you can't necessarily fit
the likelihood directly to maximize
evidence which is minimizing surprise
there's this tractable bound so this is
not something that that is being
introduced by the active inference
literature but rather variational
methods variational approximations are
being applied to the whole iguana to a
unified model of perception cognition
and
action but equation 2.5 doesn't have any
Planet it's just about beliefs at a
given moment and then what is the sort
of Base optimal move given this new
observation David go for it yeah I was
just wondering if the uh part of the
entropy formula there was related to uh
Heisenberg h
does anyone have a thought on
that you mean
the I'm I'm wondering I don't understand
the question
sorry yeah did you mean like Heisenberg
uncertainty or what yeah the uh the
uncertainty principes so in terms of the
uh functions itself related to Shannon
entropies
yeah let's look into it
more there there may be some connections
yeah it just it does deal with um fast
Warrior transform so I was just thinking
in terms of um major
modeling cool yeah in interesting
possibility the 2022 textbook doesn't go
into the
quantum uh
interpretations however maybe maybe we
can look more into it okay so this is
great for
modeling uh bound approximation yeah go
for it David oh sorry oh sorry I Wasing
bable approximation for the situation of
beliefs and a new data point coming in
so that can apply to trivially simple
systems like that have no reactivity or
sentience at all or kind of classical or
conservative ative systems like um you
know a given data point comes in it just
it just makes a linear adjustment in a
belief it also describes that real time
flow on more complex systems however it
doesn't invoke any future time points
this is just kind of like the slice of
the now so when we were interested in
modeling agents with planning that is
when we move into the expected free
energy so expected free energy is a
cousin of variational free
energy it's G it's also functional um
instead of f it's like the one after
FG its um argument that it takes is Pi
Pi is the policy prior so it's a vector
of all of the possible
policies affordances are actions that
can be taken in a moment up down left
right policies are sequences of
affordances for a given time Horizon so
for a Time Horizon of one the policy
Vector is the same as the
affordances for a Time Horizon of two
the policy Vector is of the length
affordances squared and so on so it's
like up down left right are the
affordances those are the opportunities
for action in The
Niche policies could be just one one
time step if there was no planning just
action selection or policies could be
longer like up up down up up right um so
that's about the defined time Horizon
for the model which we'll look at in
pmdp um after
this G takes in the policy prior and
it's going to update it according to how
well these policies
score on expected free
energy what gives a good score for
expected free energy here we see several
decompositions there's kind of like
three and a half decompositions because
the the second and third line are really
similar the first decomposition is in
terms of epistemic value or expected
Information Gain and pragmatic value or
utility so a lot more to say on this
just just going quickly but pragmatic
value in terms of utility is the
expected alignment between future
observations why Tilda and preferences
their preferred
observations whereas epistemic value is
about the KL Divergence between double
line beliefs about hidden States Through
Time Q on X
Tilda conditioned
upon policy either
way and observations so if the
observations coming in in are not
expected to update
beliefs these two are the same and the
KL Divergence is zero Information Gain
is zero if expected observations coming
in are expected to update beliefs like I
want to know what's on page 12 of the
book what about the policy to look on
page 12 of the book I expect those
observations to give me information even
if I don't know what direction the
information is going to be updated in
and that is assigned a high epistemic
value this is a point of
differentiation with reinforcement or
utility based models which is those
kinds of models only have pragmatic
value or utility so they need to
discover these kinds of tricks and
methods to give a
utility to Information Gain and there's
all kinds of tricks you can have her
istics like mix it up every 500 times
steps or could say give this price on
information put this price on basic
research whereas here they're kep
separate um and there's some other
representations but what's important
here is whereas
2.5 was about our
beliefs and then the data point coming
in in a
moment expected free energy is
arbitrarily forward-looking for a given
time Horizon
so a good example of of where this comes
into play is in this um active inference
epistemic chaining demo I'll put it in
the in the chat as well and probably um
linked
elsewhere
um
okay well since we're in six and and
actually like looking at how these
models are coming into play let's look
at this script but again just raise your
hand or or type it if you have any
thoughts and also note this is the PDP
python kind of uh script so RX and fur
is quite different in its style but this
is what PDP looks
like okay
first like many other Python scripts
different packages are
imported those can be
core packages or other broad packages
like numpy and it also includes specific
functionality from elsewhere in the pmtp
package um so we can kind of read this
in light of the of the
recipe so just to remind
yourself system of Interest like
situation of Interest what does the
agent look like in terms of of its
perception cognition internal States and
action and then what does the
environment look like so it's not going
to be in that order in the script but
we'll see that all those boxes will get
ticked okay first they set up the map so
this is like declaring the generative
process and it's this grid world where
there are certain cells that have
Rewards or it could be just called food
and then there's some that have cues
which are like
signals here they use M plot lib to
visualize the
grid so in in this world there's two
possible places where there could be
food or not so it's kind of like a t-
maze however the reason why it's called
epistemic chaining is that there's
different places where information can
be found and that information reduces
uncertainty about where the food is so
that's the generative
process they you should call grid world
now we get to generative
model
um
okay we're in discrete time here um pmdp
is is uh only in discret time
here's figure 7.1 so a little looking
ahead to discrete time model this is the
core sens making Motif this is what
makes something partially observable is
we have observations coming in at each
time point the observations are mapped
through a to Hidden State
s b describes how hidden States
transition through time at each time
step and D is the prior just to kick off
the chain so in the neuroimaging setting
like SPM observations are the the noisy
sensors and then s are these latent
activity patterns in the
brain that's partially observable
inference that's like a Colin filter
active inference is going to drop in on
top and add this upstairs bit but the
downstairs is exactly the saying that's
the sense making motif of observations
kind of getting mapped into latent
states where the action comes into play
is when policies intervene in how things
change we have like observations like
thermometer readings coming in at each
time step and they're getting mapped to
uh beliefs about temperature in the room
and then B is a matrix that is going to
apply to the hidden State and fold it
into the next time step so then it B has
these
slices it's kind of like index cards and
policy selection by the agent is like
picking which index card is going to be
applied to unroll into the next state so
one of the index cards might be keeping
something like just in the location
setting keep something where it is no
move then that would keep s the same
whereas there might be turn on the air
conditioner move left and then those
would be represented in the structure of
slices of B
David uh yeah I was just wondering how
this works in terms of uh weights and
values for um each portion because you
had mentioned um with active in being
applied at G as a bit would that be
considered um adding any data weight to
uh to the formulas
okay yeah good good question so again
downstairs is our like perception and
sense making here upstairs is our policy
selection applying variational inference
evidence lowerbound variational free
energy to the downstairs sensemaking
part is like a variational auto encoder
the move in active inference is to say
agents are described by The Joint
distribution of their belief about
perception cognition and action and then
we're going to take a variational free
energy on all of that so that's the
unified modeling angle that is um what
unifies like the perception inbound
signal processing problem with the
outbound control theory problem so then
the question is like well okay how how
do this is a structural model how do you
get at the weights let's see how they do
it in the demo okay so here they're
setting up the size of
Frank here they're setting up the size
and the
dimensionality of observations which are
called
OBS and hidden State factors which are
called numb States so an important thing
to to note is that
um this is like the schema or or the
sort of template
Motif however let's just say that
each grid cell uh each cell in the grid
had like a temperature a smell and a
light
variable there's modular choice in how
that is
represented you have three observations
coming in and then you could imagine
like those all project onto one hidden
State
type or you could set it up so that like
there was a hidden state for each of
those sensory
modalities and then those were or
weren't integrated so this is like map
territory this is why Toby St Clair SMI
calls this
work compositional cognitive
cartography compositional because we're
playing with Legos in category Theory
and we're composing
models cognitive because we're talking
about cognitive interfaces and things
perception cognition action and then
cartography because it's a science or
study of map making so this isn't to say
that like if you broke open an animal
you'd find this base graph it's to say
that this is a map like a subway map
that we making that has all of these
really tractable properties so there's a
lot of
places for modular degrees of freedom
and there isn't necessarily like a
correct map of a cognitive system
anymore than there would be a correct
map of of a city here they're setting up
the variables just in terms of their
length without going too much into RX
and for at this moment one of the major
challenges SL
frustrations with p DP and with modeling
is the dimensionality and making sure
all the dimensionalities work out
otherwise you get like just a bunch of
matrices that get multiplied and the
shapes don't work and it just kind of
like gives bugs
okay next they're going to State a a
Maps between observations and hidden
States so this is the downstairs sense
making part the a matrix
they make sure that its shape in terms
of rows and columns is
basically related to on one dimension
the number of hidden States and on the
other dimension the number of OB the
type of observations so you could have
five mapping on to five or you could
have one mapping on to five or you could
have five you know any any
combination then they fill
out um all Zer just to get it uh
going here there's three modalities on a
so a is kind of a is a tensor each slice
goes from observations to Hidden States
within like one frame so you can think
of it like three index cards or like
three sheets in an Excel file or a
tensor that has
three uh stacks
a a Zer is
location A1 is q1 A2 is Q2 this is zero
indexing so it's kind of like the first
element is the zero just like birthday
and so the numbers are are being filled
in and then there's this
um third third modality A3 which is the
observation of reward or not
so in how these matrices are built is
where a lot of the nitty-gritty
happens in in a okay now they move to
specifying b b is the transition model
so this is how do those hidden States
change through
time again there's the work of making
sure that the sizes and the shapes of
all the variables line up and then all
of the work of like what does Action do
all the action representation is loaded
into B and it's like when you see the
model it's like there's actually not
many places that that
uh again in this simple form there's not
many places where learning can go but
it's important to see that a is action
independent a is the mapping from obser
ations to Hidden states that can be a
recognition Direction recognizing or it
can be a generating Direction like
synthetic
data all of the efficacy of Pi all of
the efficacy and the differences that
make a difference with policy selection
influence how things change through b so
here's where we see the
actions having an impact in terms of
different be slices that can get pulled
out in the b0 which is um location just
like a z was
location we we have efficacy of actions
actions should change our location
however there's no action that the mouse
can take to change the q's and so here
the B um variables in that first first
and second modality are called
uncontrollable because there's no policy
that makes a difference for those
modalities preferences are
specified we can talk about preferences
but they play the role in contributing
to pragmatic value calculations if you
don't have any uh preference or you have
a flat preference like outcomes are
equally desirable
then epistemic value or learning or
novelty comes to dominate The behavior
whereas conversely if you have hyper
precise priors there's no epistemic
opportunities and strong preferences you
get the special case of utility
maximization then the prior over D is
specified so that was a b c d and e it
was just framed in terms of the actions
basically and any thoughts on
this okay just like in the recipe they
then turn to the the rules of the
game drawing inspiration from machine
learning and reinforcement learning all
this they use an EnV for environment
class which steps in discrete time one
by one so we defined the agent in terms
of ABC D and then they write this grid
World environment
example which is kind of like um we we
can look in more detail but this this
actually is the consequences of action
whereas before when we were defining the
agent this is its beliefs about action
what that will do and then here are the
actual consequences of choosing actions
so this begets a question like well H
how does the agent come to
know the structure the consequences of
its action that's like not addressed in
this notebook but like it's like playing
a video game and then like you're um you
were used to having up on the joystick
move you forward but then now you're in
a inverted mode where it moves you
backwards so just because the agent is
specified to have a given beliefs like
oh if I hit this button the room will
get colder but that's not necessarily A
veritical belief but that's what the
modeler is if if they're interested in
this question of how do Agents come to
learn the consequences of their action
maybe you'd set up a different model
than I'm studying agents who already
know the consequences of their auction
just like what are you trying to ask
who's the model 4 all those early
questions of chapter 6 okay all right
now we get to the active inference
part initialize an agent and an instance
of grid world again this is like chapter
six we defined the the situation of
Interest
then made the agent ABC D alphabet and
then defined the environment the
generative process grid World
M my agent is specified and here the
arguments it's taking looks a little bit
like redundance but that gives you like
a degree of freedom in specifying the
agent so you could say I want a and then
I want to customize it and so this is
just a wrapper method that bundles
together a b c and d and policy length
so that's where the expected free energy
is going to come into play Because at
each time step it's going to comp
compute uh variational free energy but
the policy length is used for the
expected free energy so in this
situation you
have five
affordances up down left right and
stay and there's
four time four four time steps is the
time Horizon of consideration so that
means the policy Vector is going to be 5
* 5 * 5 * 5 and it will sum to one
here's another point a difference to to
emphasize with reinforcement learning so
that's called this the policy space Pi
is the space of all policies that can be
selected
from in reinforcement learning or reward
learning there's another function
proposed called the utility or the
reward and it is going to give a value
to each of those points in policy space
so each policy is going to be given a
value and then
that is going to rank the policies and
then you could choose the most rewarding
most valuable policy or you could you
could probabilistically select from
policies according to their expected
value in active inference there's no
proposal of this auxilary reward
function we have our policy prior which
is like our
habit and then whether we apply G or not
which updates to the policy posterior
that policy variable is directly sampled
from so policies are selected based upon
their likelihood either they're the
likeliest thing that would happen so we
just pull from the top of the list
that's kind of like the most rewarding
policy but rather than moving through
this intermediary auxilary function
we're picking directly either the best
policy the likest policy or
probabilistically choosing from the list
that's the whole physics of um decision
making angle is there's no secondary
reward assessment it's just updating the
policy variable and then choosing from
it okay spin up the
environment and reset it just clean up
the
environment now here's the actual active
inference Loop so it's cool because
python has this semi pseudo code OD
feel history of locations is just
creating a trace or a log
variable and the number of time steps is
specified it's 10 time steps so it's
going to run for 10 steps but the
agent's window is
four so while we're within the range of
steps this is like where we get to kind
of the UDA like observe Orient decide
act because we're actually going to see
procedurally what happens within the
active inference Loop first
Q of s that
was um Q of s is Q of x q of hidden
States so here it's it's taking in
observations and it's inferring hidden
States that's Q of s
then there's policy inference so this is
sense making that's the downstairs and
then there's control that's the upstairs
and then after updating the policy prior
into the policy
posterior the actions are
selected the
movements the The Chosen action is is
kind of locked in so even though there
was a probability distribution over the
five options for movement eventually one
of them selected and this just clarifies
yeah which integer was it was it 0 1 2 3
or
four and then the implications of that
action
occur this prints a line to the terminal
just to log what
happened then the environment takes a
step predicated upon the choice of the
action of the agent and then there's
just an updating of some of the
observations and the history gets
appended
to so this is what it looks
like visualization
method so here the the agent starts here
it comes up uh oh starts in the top
left it steps here to determine which of
the
L's have the Q that's
informative it navigates to there and
then told it that the bottom spot was
the one that would have the preferred
observation
David So in terms of um modeling the map
itself and updating the agent priors for
the expectations um is there like a
library call for a different environment
or is it going to be um like a different
kind of data store for
example yeah there's a lot of ways to do
this like impdp RX Ander Etc um one
really useful articulation is right here
so let's just say that the final um
agent method is going to take on a b CDE
e one convenient approach is have like
um a bunch of a like a bunch of a
Alternatives that you generate you know
a um you
know call yeah a noisy and then and then
you make an agent Constructor and let's
say you have 10 options for a matrices
and 10 options for B matrices then you
make this a wrapper method that says
okay now spin me up all 100 agents all
10 x10
combinations of agents who have a matrix
1 through 10 and B Matrix one through 10
and then using these other kind of
methods like visualization and parameter
sweeps then you use those sorts of
methods to sweep across
combinations more modifications here
they move the two cues to hear or the
two rewards to hear um
so it's it's it's an interesting
experience but that's what chapter 6 is
like to see ultimately there's more
lines of code in this related to just
the visualization
methods sometimes it's it's
quite Curt and
concise what is actually being
specified so it's not like we're making
Mega sized models or needing to Tinker
with a wrench on a billion
parameters that's one of the
interpretability elements of active
inference
so that was their that that that was the
output of the recipe here's the recipe
to
follow just at a qualitative structural
level that may have a lot of similar
arities with other systems modeling
techniques people have learned about
like from complexity science or systems
Dynamics or other other strategies of
modeling and then we take the situation
of interest and then basically decompose
it according to the particular partition
that's what grounds this all under the
free energy principle and then more
specifically using the active ontology
so that we know that we've gotten like
the a the B the C and the D the
observation and the hidden state with
those in place you just write them in
using language models or code models to
help and
then the other functions are are shared
across
models
um in our last bit what are any like
thoughts or questions on
that e
here there there what they call a recipe
here this is like more like the UDA Loop
this is just getting into the procedure
of what happens at each time step but
also it's like just like if the
procedure for the recipe was cup of
flour a cup of sugar Etc and you had all
those ingredients
ready you'd be able to make the recipe
so the kind of functional food we're
making is an agent that's able to do
perception cognition action so if we
have all these
ingredients we have all of the precursor
materials to do this observation sampled
from the
environment move that observation into
the hidden
States through the a matrix through
variational free energy minimization
like what should I believe about
temperature given this thermometer
observation and my prior equation
2.5 calculate the expected free energy
of actions equation
2.6 policy prior reweight the policy
prior according to expected free energy
epistemic plus pragmatic value get the
policy posterior sample from
it or just pick the best one or sample
probabilistically from
it reenter that sampled action into the
generative
process that's
it and is there a similar recipe book in
terms of
rxm so
um we uh want to be building them making
an RX and F model um so we copied in
like the same recipe should apply okay
like chapter six is out a generality of
like prepare the main course prepare the
drinks set the table but then of course
it's all situational what's the main
course what's the drink what's the
what's the main table um but uh we have
Google collab notebooks drawing from
kass's code examples at learnable Loop
so if if and I'll put these these links
in the chat too so the here you can um
jump in to a
a coding
notebook and then like get all the way
on through to to seeing it in RX and fur
like here it is with running a
drone um there's some pretty major
structural differences between PDP and
RX and fur in terms of how you set the
table specify the main course Etc
um and if people want to learn more they
could explore that document and then
also
um we're working to have all of the
textbook
examples
um for the
textbook in RX infer so let's see where
where um 1.2 is
okay figure
2.1 so this is not a case of active
inference this is just a passive
inference there's beliefs about frogs
and apples like how prevalent they are
in the world that's the prior belief by
hidden States then there's a likelihood
model which is like the a matrix and
that is a mapping it's a belief about a
mapping about jumping and not jumping
and how they're related to frogs and
apples so it's kind of a 2 by two shown
here with these two bars like apples
jump 1% of the time frogs jump 81% of
the
time before we saw the observation we
believe that 10% of the items in the
world were frog
we observed a jump and then we basically
multiplied this shape by this
shape and it turns out that a jump is 81
times more likely to have come from a
frog than an apple just 81% versus
1% however we believe that apples were
nine times more likely so um something
was it was it was 9x down in in in the
um odds and then we observed something
that by 81 fold made it more likely so
it went from 9x
down to
9x up so that's the basian
update and then this is what it looks
like in RX and fur so just really
briefly here's installing Julia so
that's not related to
aroner here's install
um just showing okay have we installed
Julia here's installing the RX and fur
package and other needed
tools frog or apple it's a categorical
distribution with 0.9 and
0.1 right here
0.9.1 here's the T Matrix that's that's
what it's just being called here but the
variable names don't matter it's what
what they are and then there's this
observation that takes in those two
variables and and updates based upon
observation and then in RX Ander just
calls you just call it and you say the
data were surely a
jump and then you return the
posteriors so it's a different
style and it's one that that many of us
are still learning um however when we
have well documented examples of
everything in the textbook in RX and fur
it'll bring a lot of continuity between
the kind of engineering grade
application
framework and the learning
path so for for anybody who wants to
work in that way it it's super
helpful um okay I hope these have been
some useful pieces for people any last
um
thoughts or questions on
this um I don't want to go over time
hear too much or anything but um one
thing I have been thinking about is how
how you actually distinguish between a
continuous versus a discreet space or
time um in in that like there are you
know these limitations on your inference
procedure
um all of that calculating your your
expected free energy and and making a
decision taking an action so you're kind
of living in a discret space that's
dependent on your computational model um
when you're working in the continuous
space um which to me also raises a
question on
like in referring a policy about your
temporal breadth of of of like the
now um which is something that we kind
of do with adrenaline right so maybe
maybe we or at least it feels so
um yeah I don't know that that's just
another dimension of
modeling you're you're right is it it's
another dimension or layer and like
that's part of the fun and the
open-endedness of having such a
composable framework like temporal
thickness or um anticipation of future
agency over consideration of time
thickness like that's not here but if
you can dream it you can do it so you
could make those kinds of structural
hypotheses explicit so whether it's
making a map of a cognitive system that
does act as if it has these properties
or if you're just on a flight of fancy
or a flight of utility and you're like
could we make a policy variable
controlling this and then you just add
another node in an
edge crank it again so that's that that
is the fun is saying okay
then how how would we do that if there
was an agent that was observing it
adrenaline levels and the adrenaline
actual levels were
modifying temporality this
way maybe that's a map of
nowhere maybe it's a useful map so that
that is the whole
question and and that is why there's
such a space between the
fundamentals like the particular
partition variational free energy
expected free energy like you can't say
too much more generically than those
equations the whole point is those
equations whether in real time or in the
anticipation those equations apply to
whatever graph is
constructed but that graph could be
anything could be um a lattice of just
ones and zeros could be a continuous
automa so it's like it doesn't even have
to resemble something agentic and like
Maxwell said in Discord several weeks
ago but but I but think about all the
time he said the focus on agents has
reduced the apparent scope of active
inference because agent as we know it is
not anywhere necessarily here now one
interface that's interesting is that
like cybernetic perception action
interface but just more generally we
could talk about like Fabrics of message
passing or ecosystems of shared
intelligence
so there's kind of the the fundamentals
and then it's all about what you build
and and how the models really play out
in in their environment
so that's kind of
fun and it allows the the scaffolding
and the
externalization of cognitive hypotheses
and the consideration of alternate
cognitive
models but like the Lego set is not
opinionated on
architecture right that makes sense to
me yeah thank you for the answer cool
yeah it's a good question okay so um if
this time works for people then next
uh week will return in the third week
and that we'll we'll see if these are um
in the cohort 7 recorded or not but
we'll see um who has a feeling on what
these sessions could be about maybe we
revisit octopus math group developments
maybe we kind of look at recent updates
look at philosophy look at other uh
areas and then in um the third week for
Co
six especially with Andrew um giving the
tutorial at the workshop um and at some
conference and and uh RX and fur and
everything like we'll get down to it
with really applying it including like
everybody can make a copy of the collab
notebook so like everybody can be
running it and it really demystifies a
lot when you see it run in your browser
and you see which variables are defined
how do the variables interact what did I
put into this what do I get out of
it so it's
cool
okay thank you very much see you all
next time thanks have a good oneone bye